SAAD AHMAD ZAHID

saad.ahmad.zahid09@gmail.com • Ellicott City, MD

Summary

Solution-oriented software engineer with nine plus years of practical expertise in designing, developing, delivering, and scaling web applications. Expert in developing reliable and effective back-end solutions using Java-based technologies like Hibernate, Spring Boot and JavaServer Pages (JSP).

Also worked in Python to design adaptable solutions, used FastAPI for rapid development of APIs for one of our enterprise level project. I have managed development teams of different types for small and large-scale projects, mentored them and architected the solutions, enabling the team members to deliver quality work.

I would like to offer my expertise to develop and scale the solutions for the growth of your organization.

Experience

CrawlNow

Full Stack Software Engineer

04/2022 - Present

As an experienced software engineer, I assist CrawlNow in their efforts to design, deliver and grow web solutions. I recently collaborated with a
CrawlNow client to develop a map-based real estate portal that is utilized by hundreds of thousand users. On this portal, property agents can
list their properties, while users may search for the property they need and communicate with the owner along with many other product
features. We have built, optimized, and monetized this product using technologies like Java, Spring Boot, React.js, PostgreSQL, AWS, and
Kubernetes.

GeoViz Inc

Senior Software Engineer

03/2018 - 03/2022

- Utilized Java Spring Boot to implement a micro services architecture for the backend of GeoViz's flagship product.
- Implemented APIs with Spring MVC to handle CRUD operations for profiles.
- Amazon RDS (using PostgreSQL or MySQL) as the relational database to store data.
- Content stored in Amazon S3 buckets and served quickly via Amazon CloudFront.
- Utilized Apache Kafka for handling real-time data streams and quickly loading previews.
- Content delivery accelerated globally using Google Cloud CDN in tandem with Amazon CloudFront.
- User decisions stored in Amazon DynamoDB for fast access and retrieval.
- · Visualization dashboard deployed on Google App Engine for scalability.
- Content uploaded to Amazon S3 buckets.
- Encoding jobs managed via AWS Lambda functions for serverless processing.
- Integration with Google Cloud Storage for backup and archival.

NetSol Technologies

Software Engineer

08/2014 - 02/2018

- · Developed a robust and secure online banking portal using Django for the backend.
- Transactions and account data stored in PostgreSQL with data access handled by Django ORM.
- Deployed microservices in Docker containers orchestrated with Kubernetes.
- Authored comprehensive API documentation for python components.
- · Created user manuals and guides for the web portal, ensuring that end-users have clear instructions and resources.
- Implemented a CI/CD pipeline using Jenkins. Automated unit tests written in Python (using pytest).
- Implemented analytics dashboards using Python to visualize key financial metrics for internal stakeholders.
- Conducted regular meetings with the Customer Support team to understand common user issues and gather feedback.
- Regularly engaged in rigorous code reviews using tools like Bitbucket or GitHub, ensuring code quality and maintainability.
- Held monthly meetings with key stakeholders and investors, providing updates on the platform's technical progress and addressing any concerns.

Education

FAST NUCES

Bachelor of Science, Software Engineering

2010 - 2014

SKILLS

Java · Python · AWS · GCP · ElasticSearch · Terraform · Redis · EC2 · Lambda · CloudWatch · AWS Cloud Front · Docker · Kafka · JSON · JavaScript · Typescript · MySQL · NoSQL · SQL Server · React · HTML · CSS · Git